<resources>
    <string name="app_name">DrivingQuiz</string>
    <string name="openNavBar">Navigation Drawer Open</string>
    <string name="closeNavBAr">Navigation Drawer Close</string>
    <string name="alcoholAndDrugsInfo">
        In this article you\'ll find out the blood alcohol concentration (BAC) limits for NSW, whether you can calculate what your BAC is, and whether you can speed up the elimination of alcohol from your system so you can drive again sooner.

It is always safest to not have a drink at all before you drive as any amount of alcohol impairs your ability to drive. Alcohol is a depressant which means it slows down your ability for your brain to work.

New South Wales has three different limits for blood alcohol concentration depending on your type of licence. Put simply:

Learner, P1 or P2 drivers (or equivalent) from anywhere in the world: Zero

Drivers of vehicles with a GVM greater than 13.9 tonnes, or carrying dangerous goods, or carrying paying passengers (e.g. taxi, bus): 0.02ml/100ml of blood

All other licences: 0.05ml/100ml of blood.

Learner drivers are developing their skills therefore the reduced limit is in force until they have proven themselves able to drive. This is because alcohol affects reaction times and learner and P-plate drivers already have to cope with many situations they may not be familiar or comfortable with, and that take their entire concentration.

\n\nHidden alcohol
\nSome products such as medicines, mouthwashes and food can contain alcohol without you knowing. While you can try to convince a court that you didn\'t have an alcoholic drink or other substance with the purpose of consuming alcohol there is no guarantee you will win, and it could cost you a substantial amount in legal fees.\n

Check the ingredients and if in doubt, don\'t drive. You can ask your doctor if he or she has prescribed medication for you whether it\'s safe for you to drive.

\n\nCan you calculate your blood alcohol concentration?
\nThe amount of alcohol absorbed and retained by your blood is impossible to calculate because there are too many contributing factors. As the alcohol is processed by your stomach, your blood alcohol concentration can continue to rise for up to two hours after you have stopped drinking. Your blood alcohol level is influenced by all of the following:

\n\nGender
\nA woman the same height and weight as a man, drinking the same amount, will have a higher blood alcohol concentration

\n\nAge
\nYounger people tend to process alcohol more slowly

\n\nLiver function
\nA healthy liver processes alcohol much more quickly than an unhealthy liver, which means that if you are healthy you can register a spike in blood alcohol much sooner than someone with a compromised liver

\n\nSize/weight
\nA larger person will have a lower blood alcohol concentration than a smaller person on the same amount of alcohol

\n\nFood intake
\nA recent meal will slow the absorption of alcohol. Drinking alcohol on an empty stomach means the alcohol is absorbed quickly. Eating after drinking doesn\'t reduce your blood alcohol level.

\n\nFitness
\nYour overall health and fitness affects your blood alcohol concentration. If you are run-down, fatigued or general unfit your blood alcohol concentration can be higher

\n\nType of drinks consumed
\nSome drinks are high concentration in relation to their volume and can have insidious levels of alcohol. Alcohol concentration can vary from as little as a couple of percent up to more than 40% in some spirits.

\n\nVolume of drink consumed
\nIt\'s often difficult to tell exactly how much you\'ve drunk because drinks come in non-standard measures, they get topped up, they could be mixed and so on.

\n\nGetting your blood alcohol concentration back to zero
\nYour physiology will determine how long it will take for your blood alcohol concentration to return to normal. If you stop drinking at 2am it can be 8pm at night before you are down to zero if you have drunk heavily. Many people are booked for drink driving the morning after they have been drinking. Even with a moderate level of alcohol it can be late morning or early afternoon before you are safe to drive again. The only way to get your blood alcohol down is to wait. Adding other liquid does not affect your body\'s ability to eliminate the alcohol.

\n\nWhat speeds up alcohol breakdown in your body?
\nA healthy liver will process around 1 standard drink per hour. You will also sweat, breathe and urinate out small amounts of alcohol, but this is minor in comparison to what the liver does, so even a sauna will not make much difference. You might also think that taking a drug that speeds up your metabolism, such as cocaine, might help, but this is not the case, either: alcohol binds to cocaine, keeping both of them in your system longer.

\nTime is the only thing that will sober you up. Water will reduce your hangover by preventing dehydration and helping eliminate toxins, but it won\'t speed up the process. Neither will a shower, black coffee, food or any type of other substance.

\n\nBreath testing
It\'s always an offence to refuse a police breath test. If you are convicted of driving with a blood alcohol level above the limit you will be fined, you will lose your licence and you could be sent to prison.

\n\nThe effects of alcohol on your driving or riding
\nAlcohol will slow down your reaction times. It gives you more confidence, but less ability. It makes it easier for you to misjudge other drivers\' speed and direction, and for you to judge what speed you are approaching obstacles on the road.

If you are riding a motorbike, alcohol affects your balance.

\n\nCrash severity
\nWhen drivers have been drinking, the crashes they are involved in are generally more severe. On Thursday, Friday and Saturday nights the proportion of serious injury crashes involving alcohol rises to about 50% - it\'s the leading cause of serious vehicle accidents.

\n\nUsing legal drugs and medications and their effect on your driving
Legal drugs and medications can have a similar affect on your driving as alcohol. If you mix legal or illegal drugs and alcohol if can have a dramatically more severe effect on your motor coordination skills and other skills required for driving.

\n\nDriving in Australia on a New Zealand or UK licence?
\nBe especially careful if you have moved from New Zealand or the UK their limit is much more than ours at 0.08 (80mg per 100ml of blood, although New Zealand\'s is changing on 1 December 2014 to the same as here), and what might have previously been legal for you to drive within New Zealand or the UK might not be under the limit here. Also, New Zealand has a zero limit for those aged 16-19, but not if you are 20 or older, regardless of the licence type.
    </string>

    <string name="Intersections">
        This article covers intersections, roundabouts, lane use and traffic light rules in New South Wales, including where road traffic intersects with other traffic like pedestrians, cyclists and trams/light rail.

\n\nIntersections
\nIntersections will be controlled by traffic lights or give way and stop signs, or they could be uncontrolled with no lights or signs.

When there\'s a STOP sign it is compulsory to stop even if you think you can see the way is clear. If it\'s a GIVE WAY sign, then you must be prepared to stop if there\'s other traffic coming. You must always use your indicator to let other road users know what you are doing including when turning, overtaking or changing lanes. Even if you don\'t think you see another vehicle, there might be a bike or pedestrian that you haven\'t seen.

Instructions from a police officer override signs and lights at an intersection. If there is a traffic controller in the intersection you must obey what they tell you.

As you approach an intersection you should check for traffic on your left and right at all times. If it\'s a crossroads, look for traffic coming towards you that might turn right in front of you. Pay particular attention as cyclists and motorcyclists are more difficult to see at intersections because of their smaller profile. Look twice in case you missed something on your first glance.

If there are no traffic signals at an intersection and it is unmarked then you must always give way to your right. As you approach the intersection drive at a speed that gives you enough time to stop if traffic suddenly appears. Look for clues of traffic coming as you approach the intersection - for example you might see dust rising off the road, or if you have your windows down you might hear approaching vehicles.

\n\nunmarked intersection

If you are at an unmarked crossroads and you are turning right then you must give way to any vehicle coming from straight ahead and turning left, and any vehicle coming from the right that\'s going straight ahead or turning right.

\n\nright turn at crossroads

If you are turning right at a T-intersection from the bottom of the T, then you must give way to your left and right to vehicles crossing the top of the T.

turning out of a T-intersection

This second example of an unmarked T-intersection demonstrates that even if someone is turning in front of you you must wait for them if you are on the bottom of the T.

two cars turning right at T-intersection

When you are facing another vehicle at a crossroads, if you are turning right you must wait for any vehicles coming straight through or turning left. Therefore in the diagram below vehicle P has right of way over vehicle O.

\n\ngive way at crossroads

\nstop signIf a STOP or GIVE WAY sign has been knocked down, for example, as the result of an accident, the line marked across the road indicates the meaning of the sign, and must be obeyed. If there\'s a stop sign, but no line then stop before coming to, and as near to, the intersection as possible. You can always edge forwards to get a better view after you\'ve stopped.

Vehicle at a STOP sign have the lowest priority of all other signs at an intersection. In the example below, vehicle O must wait for all other vehicles to complete their manoeuvres.

stop sign at crossroads

If both opposing vehicles have the same class of sign, e.g. two stop signs or two give way signs, then the give way rules apply.

two stop signs at crossroads

If both vehicles are turning right then they don\'t need to cross each other\'s paths.

two vehicles turning right

When you come to an intersection and the road beyond is choked with vehicles going in the same direction you must wait until there is room to completely cross the intersection, even if your traffic light turns green.

\n\nqueuing traffic at green light
\nThe vehicles with the green light must wait because the road ahead is blocked
When travelling on a laned roadway, right turns must be made from the right-hand lane unless there are right-turning arrows in other lanes. In the example below you can see traffic turning from a one-way street. The left-hand lane traffic can also turn right. Any vehicle wanting to turn into the road at X would use the left hand lane.

one-way street right turn from both lanes

If there are no lanes marked on a one-way street and you want to turn right, make the right turn from the right-hand side of the road, as shown in diagram R below.

turning right from a one-way street

The diagram below shows a marked pedestrian crossing at an intersection. There is also a STOP sign at the intersection. Even if you have already stopped for a pedestrian you must stop again at the STOP line.

stop sign and pedestrian crossing

At intersections where the road turns, watch to see who has the give way or stop sign to determine who has right-of-way. In the example below, the car at J must wait for the other cars.

give way at turn

\n\nRoundabouts
\nAs you approach a roundabout you will see a roundabout sign like this

roundabout sign

The rules for a roundabout are that you must always give way to the right and you must use the appropriate lane. You can see in the photo below that the right-hand lane can be used for turning right and going straight ahead, whereas the left-hand lane can be used for turning left or going straight ahead.

roundabout

In the image below if you want to go straight ahead at the roundabout you would signal left as you pass point O.

roundabout signalling

In the following example the motorbike should be cautious about the car on the roundabout as it could be leaving the roundabout and therefore cut across in front of the motorcyclist.



\n\nThe rules for signalling at roundabouts
\nWhen turning left, approach the roundabout in the left lane indicating left and continue indicating while you make the turn. Exit the roundabout in the left lane.

When going straight ahead, approach the roundabout in any lane marked for going straight ahead and don\'t indicate. Indicate left as you pass the exit before the one you want to take. Leave the roundabout in the same lane as the one you entered in.

When turning right, approach the roundabout in any lane marked for turning right (usually the right-hand lane), indicating right. As you pass the exit before the one you want to take, signal left. If there are two lanes on your exit road then you will exit onto the right-hand lane.

If you want to travel completely around the roundabout it\'s like an extended right-hand turn. Simply keep the right signal on until you\'ve passed the exit before you want to exit the roundabout, then exit into the right-hand lane, like in this diagram.



Therefore in the image below, the red car is not in the right position to turn right at the roundabout because is in the left-hand lane.

wrong lane on the roundabout

\n\nMerging
\nWhen entering a freeway or motorway from an on-ramp you should merge like a zip: match your speed to that of the traffic on the freeway and look for a gap to slot yourself in. If you are following other vehicles onto the freeway don\'t force yourself into the line of traffic. Merge one-by-one, allowing other vehicles on the freeway enough time to adjust their position. If you try to merge more slowly than the cars on the freeway you create a dangerous situation as vehicles on the freeway will need to brake to adjust to your speed. This increases the risk of nose-to-tail accidents and slows all traffic up, i.e. by merging slowly you contribute to traffic congestion.

When two roads merge into one road, the vehicle that has to cross the lane line must give way.

If two lanes merge into one without a lane line, the vehicle that is ahead has right of way.

merging with no lane line



\n\nTraffic lights
\nAt red traffic lights you must stop if it\'s safe to do so then wait behind the line until the light turns green.

Traffic light phases are set so that, at the speed limit, vehicles should be able to pull up safely when the light turns yellow without having to drive through the intersection while the light is red. Red light cameras will only trigger if you enter the intersection when the light is red.

red light speed camera ahead 60kph

Traffic lights have the phasing red, green, yellow, red. On some intersections you will find a red turning arrow which means you can turn on a red light if the turning arrow is green.

green turning arrow

The signal below shows that traffic going straight ahead or turning right must stop, whereas traffic turning left can go (but must wait if there are any pedestrians crossing the road).

green filter light

A green light means you can turn left (if there are no crossing pedestrians), go straight ahead, and turn right (if you give way to traffic coming towards you.

green light

At some intersections with lights a left turn is permitted after stopping, and it will be shown in a sign like the one below.

amber light stop left turn on red

You must not make a u-turn at traffic lights unless there is a \'U-TURN PERMITTED\' sign.

Even if it\'s the middle of the night and there is no one coming, you must not go through a red light.

If there is another vehicle blocking the exit where you want to go, you must not go, even if you have a green light.

Temporary traffic lights are sometimes installed at roadworks and they should be treated as any other traffic light. The sign indicates where it is safe to stop. Also, some automated lights have a sensor for vehicles waiting at a red light so they know to turn the lights green again after a certain period of time. Parking forward of this sensor may mean the light does not change green.

temporary traffic lights

Giving way at railway crossings
When approaching a railway level crossing that displays a STOP sign then you must stop.

railway level crossing sign

If there are boom gates down and flashing red lights then you must also stop, and you must not cross the railway until the lights have stopped flashing and the boom gates have lifted. Trains cannot brake quickly so won\'t be able to stop if there is a vehicle blocking the tracks.

If the railway level crossing has a red triangle then you must slow down and be prepared to stop if there\'s a train coming. Even if the signals are not flashing, it\'s a good idea to slow down and check left and right before you cross.

railway level crossing

If you can\'t cross the railway level crossing without clearing the crossing completely (e.g. there is traffic backed up the other side of the crossing), don\'t cross until it\'s clear.

Giving way to other road users
If you are turning at an intersection and pedestrians are crossing the road, you must give way to them.

If you come to an intersection in Sydney with a Light Rail vehicle about to enter you must wait until the intersection is clear.

tram from rear with tram sign

Light rail vehicle lanes are marked with this sign:

light rail sign

When exiting a driveway you must give way to bicycles, vehicles and pedestrians.

\n\nLane use
\nIf there are no lanes marked on a road, drive near to the left hand edge. If there are lanes, then you will adjust your position based on traffic around you. For example, if you are overtaking a line of parked cars you will move more to the right of your lane; if there\'s a large vehicle coming towards you, you might move left in your lane. You will predominantly travel in the middle of your lane, though.There are painted lines in the middle of the road to tell you what you can do.

On a multi-lane road with a speed limit of 80kph or more, you should drive in the left-hand lane unless you are overtaking.

The road in the image below has a double unbroken dividing line therefore the purple car can only cross it to turn into a driveway (assuming it\'s safe to do so), not to overtake another vehicle. The line is broken where there is a side street.

double unbroken lines

The same would apply even on a country road with a double undivided centre line - it means you are not allowed to overtake because it could be dangerous to do so due to the road layout or visibility.

double unbroken white line in the country

If the road has a broken white line on your side of the centre, then you can also cross it to overtake.

broken white line

You can cross an unbroken line to the left if it is to turn into an intersection

turning left over unbroken line

When riding on a single lane road a motorbike can legally use any part of the lane.

\n\nChanging lanes
\nBefore changing lanes you must first check your mirrors, then signal your intentions, then check your mirrors and blind spot, then make the manoeuvre. Even if you can\'t see any other road users around you must still indicate for at least five seconds because there could be a motorcyclist, cyclist or other road user you haven\'t seen.

As you pull away from the kerb the last thing you should look over your shoulder and check your mirrors. This helps you avoid hitting other road users.

\n\nTransit lanes
\ntransit laneA transit lane is a lane reserved for vehicles with defined minimum number of occupants. For example, a T2 lane must have a driver and at least one other occupant whereas a T3 lane must have a driver and at least two other occupants. T2 and T3 lanes can usually be used by cyclists, motorcyclists and buses, too.

If you drive into a transit lane without the required number of passengers you will be fined if caught.

If they are time-limited then the operational times will be displayed on the sign, for example 6am-10am Monday to Friday.

You are allowed to travel in a transit lane with less than the required occupants if you are turning left into a side street or driveway, but only for 100m before the turning.

\n\nMedian lanes or median strips
\nstraight road from median strip no cars.

A median lane is a lane designed to allow vehicles to wait to turn right, or vehicles from a side road to enter and wait for a gap, without holding up the flow of traffic.

The median lane may have turning bays. If your vehicle won\'t obstruct the path of other vehicles you can turn into the median lane and wait. In the case of the diagram below, vehicles Y and O can both move into the lane and wait without crossing each other\'s trajectories.

turning from a media lane turning bay

You are not allowed to park in a median strip.

\n\nBus lanes
\nYou must not drive in a bus lane if it is only reserved for buses unless you are driving a taxi or hire car.

bus lane sign

Bus lanes can be indicated by several different types of signs indicating the direction of the bus lane and (if it\'s not a 24-hour bus lane) what times it is in operation. Painted road markings will reinforce exactly where the lane is.

bus lane

\n\nEmergency lane
\nIf you break down on a freeway then you should move over to the emergency lane on the shoulder on the left (the hard shoulder), then call for help
    </string>
    <string name="DefensiveDriving">
        Depending on where you are in the world you will hear about either the two-second rule or the three-second rule. In the UK and New Zealand, the two-second rule is promoted, whereas here we use the three-second rule. The distance is checked by timing three seconds from when the back of the vehicle in front clears a particular place and then the front of your vehicle passes that place.

Maintaining a gap of three seconds between you and the vehicle in front is definitely safer than two seconds, but there comes a limit of pragmatic motoring, i.e. keeping 3 seconds behind adds 50% more distance between vehicles which actually contributes to traffic jams. Although, so do nose-to-tail accidents which would be virtually eliminated if we all followed at least 3 seconds behind the vehicle in front.

At night it is more difficult to judge distances so increasing the gap to four seconds can help.

\n\nStopping distances
\nWe covered braking distances on motorbikes in this article. Your stopping distance is your thinking (or reaction) distance plus your braking distance.

\n\nReaction distance
\nYour reaction distance will be longer if you are tired, distracted (e.g. by loud music, children, or your own thoughts), have been drinking (check drink driving limits here), have taken drugs (read about driving and drugs here), have taken some kinds of medication (see our article here), or are older.

For example, if you take one second to react you will travel 14m at 50kph. At two seconds this is 28m. Two seconds is considered to be fairly common if you are not expecting something to happen; one second would mean you are very alert and half a second would mean you expected the event to happen (e.g. in drag racing a 0.5s reaction time is considered a \'perfect\' reaction time when the race starts).

\n\nBraking distance
\nAt the end of your reaction time is when you press the brake, and then a number of things happen. Your vehicle has a brake balance set which will divert more of the braking power to the front tyres than the rear tyres. Very few road cars have any ability to change this in the cabin.

\n\nNo ABS or other electronics
\nYour braking power will be diverted in proportion to the front wheels and back wheels. Assuming the brakes are of equal performance each side), each front wheel gets the same braking power and each back wheel gets the same braking power. If one front wheel has less grip than the other it will start locking (skidding first). As there is no ABS (anti-lock brakes) you will need to cadence brake (pump the brakes as you feel them start to lock) to get the best braking power.

If there is a difference in the strength of the brakes on either side, one side will consistently lock before the other and could cause you to spin.

This is why you should avoid heavy braking on wet roads.

\n\nABS, but no other electronics
\nIf you brake enough to lock one or more wheels ABS will reduce the braking power in a fraction of a second to stop it locking, but also reduces it on all wheels.

ABS + electronic brakeforce distribution
EBD is an electronic system that knows when the braking friction has been overcome on one wheel and then diverts more braking power to wheels that are still turning until they start to lock. You get better braking performance without having to push the brake pedal as hard.

\nABS + EBD is the optimal combination for rapid braking.

\n\nMechanical and tyres
\nIn a vehicle with four wheels you have four contact patches on the road that provide friction to help slow down the tyre. You also have four wheels that will have brake discs or drums that provide friction to slow down the rotation.

Your braking performance is ultimately down to how much friction your tyres have on the road. Worn tyres won\'t have as much grip. Softer tyres will have more grip (but will wear easier). Heavily cambered tyres (tyres leaning in at the top) don\'t provide as much braking performance in a straight line as tyres that are vertical.

Vehicles will worn suspension will \'dive\' under brakes putting more weight over the front wheels. Vehicles that maintain a good weight distribution between front and back wheels get more effective braking.

\n\nSlippery surfaces
\nIf it starts to rain the roads can become very slippery as the layer of grime and oil on the surface will mix with water and create a slick film that makes corners more difficult to negotiate. If it\'s wet or you are towing a trailer then 4-6 seconds is recommended. If it\'s icy it can take up to ten times as long to stop. Sand and gravel act like marbles on the road. Wet leaves and wet road markings are slippery, too.
    </string>
</resources>